overhill and underhill.
There were many paths that led up into those mountains and many passes over
them, but most of the paths were cheats and deceptions and led nowhere or to bad
ends. And most of the passes were infested by evil things and dreadful
dangers. The dwarves and the hobbit, helped by the wise advice of Eland and
the knowledge and memory of Gandalf, took the right road to the right pass.
Long days after they had climbed out of the valley and left the last homely
house miles behind, they were still going up and up and up. It was a hard
path and a dangerous path, a crooked way and a lonely and along. Now they could
look back over the lands they had left laid out behind them far below. Far, far
away in the west, where things were blue and fate, Bilbo knew there lay his own
country of safe and comfortable things, and his little hobbit hole. He shivered.
It was getting bitter cold up here, and the wind came shrill among the rocks.
Boulders, too, at times came galloping down the mountain sides, let loose by
midday sun upon the snow, and passed among them, which was lucky, or over
their heads, which was alarming. The nights were comfortless and chill, and
they did not dare to sing or talk too loud, for the echoes were uncanny, and
the silence seemed to dislike being broken, except by the noise of water,
and the whale of wind and the crack of stone. The summer is getting on down
below, thought Bilbo, and haymaking is going on in picnics. They will be
harvesting and blackberrying before we even begin to go down the other side at
this rate. And the others were thinking equally gloomy thoughts, although when
they had said goodbye to Eland in the high hope of a midsummer morning, they
had spoken gayely of the passage of the mountains, and of riding swift across
the lands beyond. They had thought of coming to the secret door in the lonely
mountain. Perhaps that very next last moon of autumn, and perhaps it will be
Duran's day, they had said. Only Gandalf had shaken his head and said nothing.
Tors had not passed that way for many years, but Gandalf had, and he knew how
evil and danger had grown and threatened in the wild, since the dragons had
driven men from the lands, and the goblins had spread in secret after the
battle of the mines of Moria. Even the good plans of wise wizards like Gandalf,
and of good friends like Eland go astray sometimes when you are off on dangerous
adventures over the edge of the wild.
And Gandalf was a wise enough wizard to know it. He knew that something
unexpected might happen, and he hardly dared to hope that they would pass
without fearful adventure over those great tall mountains with lonely peaks
and valleys where no king ruled. They did not. All was well, until one day
they met a thunderstorm, more than a thunderstorm, a thunder battle. You know
how terrific a really big thunderstorm can be down in the land and in a river
valley. especially at times when two great thunderstorms meet and clash. More
terrible still are thunder and lightning in the mountains at night, when storms
come up from east and west and make war.
The lightning splinters on the peaks, and rocks shiver, and great crashes
split the air and go rolling and tumbling into every cave and hollow, and
the darkness is filled with overwhelming noise and sudden light.
Bilbo had never seen or imagined anything of the kind. They were high up
in a narrow place with a dreadful fall into a dim valley at one side of them.
There they were sheltering under a hanging rock for the night, and he lay
beneath a blanket and shook from head to toe. When he peeped out in the lightning
flashes, he saw that across the valley the stone giants were out and were
hurling rocks at one another for a game, and catching them, and tossing them down
into the darkness, where they smashed among the trees far below, or splintered
into little bits with a bang. Then came a wind and a rain, and the wind whipped
the rain and the hail about in every direction, so that an overhanging rock
was no protection at all. Soon they were getting drenched, and their ponies were
standing with their heads down and their tails between their legs, and some of
them were winning with fright. They could hear the giants galling and
shouting all over the mountain sides.
"This won't do at all," said Thoren. "If we don't get blown off, or drowned, or
struck by lightning, we shall be picked up by some giant and kicked skyhigh for
a football." The mountain path. Well, if you know of anywhere better, take us
there, said Gandalf, who was feeling very grumpy and was far from happy about
the giants himself. The end of their argument was that they sent Feelely and
Killy to look for a better shelter. They had very sharp eyes, and being the
youngest of the doors by some 50 years, they usually got these sort of jobs,
when everybody could see that it was absolutely no use sending Bilbo. There
is nothing like looking. If you want to find something, or so Thoren said to the
young dwarfs, "You certainly usually find something if you look, but it is
not always quite the something you were after, so it proved on this occasion."
Soon Feelely and Keely came crawling back, holding on to the rocks in the
wind. "We have found a dry cave," they said, not far round the next corner, and
ponies and all could get inside. "Have you thoroughly explored it?" said the
wizard, who knew that caves up in the mountains were seldom unoccupied.
"Yes, yes," they said, though everybody knew they could not have been long about
it. They had come back too quick. It isn't all that vague, and it does not go
far back. That, of course, is the dangerous part about caves. You don't
know how far they go back sometimes, or where a passage behind may lead to, or
what is waiting for you inside, but now Feelely and Killies knew seemed good
enough. So they all got up and prepared to move. The wind was howling and the
thunder still growling, and they had a business getting themselves and their
ponies along. Still, it was not very far to go, and before long they came to a
big rock standing out into the path. If he stepped behind, he found a low arch
in the side of the mountain. There was just room to get the ponies through with
a squeeze when they had been unpacked and unsaddled. As they passed under the
arch, it was good to hear the wind and the rain outside instead of all about
them, and to feel safe from the giants and their rocks.
But the wizard was taking no risks. He lit up his wand as he did that day in
Bilbo's dining room that seemed so long ago, if you remember, and by its light
they explored the cave from end to end.
It seemed quite a fair size, but not too large and mysterious. It had a dry floor
and some comfortable nooks. At one end there was room for the police, and there
they stood, mighty glad of the change, steaming and champing in their nose
bags. Oin and Gloin wanted to light a fire at the door to dry their clothes,
but Gandalf would not hear of it. So they spread out their wet things on the
floor and got dry ones out of their bundles. Then they made their blankets
comfortable, got out their pipes and blew smoke rings, which Gandalf turned
into different colors and set dancing up by the roof to amuse them. They talked
and talked and forgot about the storm and discussed what each would do with
his share of the treasure when they got it, which at the moment did not seem so
impossible. And so they dropped off to sleep one by one, and that was the last
time that they used the ponies, packages, baggages, tools, and
paraphernelia that they had brought with them. It turned out a good thing that
night that they had brought little Bilbo with them after all, for somehow he
could not go to sleep for a long while, and when he did sleep, he had very nasty
dreams. He dreamed that a crack in the wall at the back of the cave got bigger
and bigger and opened wider and wider, and he was very afraid, but could not
call out or do anything but lie and look. Then he dreamed that the floor of
the cave was giving way, and he was slipping, beginning to fall down, down
goodness knows where, too. At that he woke up with a horrible start, and found
that part of his dream was true. A crack had opened at the back of the cave, and
was already a wide passage. He was just in time to see the last of the pony's
tails disappearing into it. Of course, he gave a very loud yell, as loud a yell
as a hobbit can give, which is surprising for their size. Out jumped
the goblins, big goblins, great uglyl looking goblins, lots of goblins, before
you could say rocks and blocks. There were six to each dwarf at least, and two
even for Bilbo, and they were all grabbed and carried through the crack
before you could say tinder and flint.
but not Gandalf.
Bilbo's yell had done that much good. It had wakened him up wide in a splintered
second, and when goblins came to grab him, there was a terrific flash like
lightning in the cave, a smell like gunpowder, and several of them fell
dead. The crack closed with a snap, and Bilbo and the dwarves were on the wrong
side of it. Where was Gandalf? of that neither they nor the goblins had any
idea, and the goblins did not wait to find out. They seized Bilbo and the
dwarves, and hurried them along. It was deep, deep, dark, such as only goblins
that have taken to living in the heart of the mountains can see through. The
passages there were crossed and tangled in all directions, but the goblins knew
their way as well as you do to the nearest post office, and the way went
down and down, and it was most horribly stuffy. The goblins were very rough and
pinched unmercifully, and chuckled and laughed in their horrible stony voices,
and Bilbo was more unhappy even than when the troll had picked him up by his
toes. He wished again and again for his nice bright hobbit hole. Not for the
last time. Now there came a glimmer of a red light before them. The goblins began
to sing or croak, keeping time with the flap of their flat feet on the stone,
and shaking their prisoners as well.
Clap, snap, the black crack. Grip, grab, pinch, nab, and down, down to goblin
town. You go, my lad.
Clash, crash, crush, smash, hammer in tongs, knock her in gongs, pound far
underground. Ho ho, my lad. Swish, smack, whip, crack, batter and beat,
yammer and bleet. Work, work, nor dare to shook, while goblins quaff and
goblins laugh round and round far underground below, my lad. It sounded
truly terrifying. The walls echo to the clap sm and the crush smash and to the
ugly laughter of their ho ho ho my lad.
The general meaning of the song was only too plain. For now the goblins took out
whips and whipped them with a swish smack and set them running as fast as
they could in front of them. And more than one of the dwarves were already
yammering and bleeding like anything when they stumbled into a big cavern.
It was lit by a great red fire in the middle and by torches along the walls,
and it was full of goblins. They all laughed and stamped and clapped their
hands when the dwarves with poor little Bilbo at the back and nearest to the
whips came running in while the goblin drivers whooped and cracked their whips
behind. The ponies were already there, huddled in a corner, and there were all
the baggages and packages lying broken open, and being rummaged by goblins, and
smelt by goblins, and fingered by goblins, and quarreled over by goblins.
I am afraid that was the last they ever saw of those excellent little ponies,
including a jolly, sturdy little white fellow that had lent to Gandalf, since
his horse was not suitable for the mountain paths. for goblins eat horses
and ponies and donkeys and other much more dreadful things, and they are
always hungry." Just now, however, the prisoners were thinking only of
themselves. The goblins changed their hands behind their backs and linked them
all together in a line, and dragged them to the far end of the cavern, with
little Bilbo tugging at the end of the row. There in the shadows on a large
flat stone sat a tremendous goblin with a huge head and armed goblins were
standing around him carrying the axes and the bent swords that they use. Now
goblins are cruel, wicked, and bad-hearted. They make no beautiful
things, but they make many clever ones.
They can tunnel and mine as well as any but the most skilled dwarves when they
take the trouble, though they are usually untidy and dirty. hammers, axes,
swords, daggers, pickaxes, tongs, and also instruments of torture. They make
very well or get other people to make to their design. Prisoners and slaves that
have to work till they die for want of air and light. It is not unlikely that
they invented some of the machines that have since troubled the world,
especially the ingenious devices for killing large numbers of people at once,
for wheels and engines and explosions always delighted them, and also not
working with their own hands more than they could help. But in those days, and
those wild parts, they had not advanced, as it is called, so far. They did not
hate dwarves especially no more than they hated everybody and everything and
particularly the orderly and prosperous.
In some parts wicked dwarves had even made alliances with them. But they had a
special grudge against Dorin's people because of the war which you have heard
mentioned but which does not come into this tale. And anyway, goblins don't
care who they catch, as long as it is done smart and secret, and the prisoners
are not able to defend themselves. "Who are these miserable persons?" said the
great cobblin. "Dwarves, and this," said one of the drivers, pulling at Bilbo's
chain, so that he fell forward onto his knees. "We found them sheltering in our
front porch." "What do you mean by it?"
said the great goblin, turning to Thoren. Up to no good, I'll warrant.
Spying on the private business of my people, I guess. Thieves, I shouldn't be
surprised to learn. Murderers and friends of elves, not unlikely. Come,
what have you got to say?
Thor and the dwarf at your service, he replied. It was merely a polite nothing.
Of the things which you suspect, and imagine we had no idea at all. We
sheltered from a storm in what seemed a convenient cave and unused. Nothing was
further from our thoughts than inconveniencing goblins in any way
whatever. That was true enough. Um, said the great goblin. So you say, might I
ask what you were doing up in the mountains at all and where you were
coming from and where you were going to?
In fact, I should like to know all about you. Not that it will do you much good,
nor Oaken Shield, I know too much about your folk already, but let's have the
truth, or I will prepare something particularly uncomfortable for you.
We were on a journey to visit our relatives, our nephews and nieces and
first, second, and third cousins, and the other descendants of our
grandfathers who live on the east side of these truly hospitable mountains,"
said Thorin, not quite knowing what to say all at once in a moment, when
obviously the exact truth would not do at all. "He is a liar, oh truly
tremendous one," said one of the drivers. Several of our people were
struck by lightning in the cave when we invited these creatures to come below,
and they are as dead as stones. Also, he has not explained this. He held out the
sword which Thoren had worn, the sword which came from the trolls layer. The
great goblin gave a truly awful howl of rage when he looked at it, and all his
soldiers nashed their teeth, clashed their shields, and stamped. They knew
the sword at once. He had killed hundreds of goblins in its time when the
fair elves of Gondolan hunted them in the hills or did battle before their
walls. They had called it Orcrist goblin cleaver, but the goblins called it
simply biter. They hated it and hated worse anyone that carried it. Murderers
and elf friends, the great goblins shouted. slash them, beat them, bite
them, nash them, take them away to dark holes full of snakes, and never let them
see the light again. He was in such a rage that he jumped off his seat and
himself rushed at Thoren with his mouth open. Just at that moment, all the
lights in the cavern went out, and the great fire went off, poof, into a tower
of blue glowing smoke right up to the roof that scattered piercing white
sparks all among the goblins.
The yells and yammering, croaking, jibbering and jabbering, howls, growls
and curses, shrieking and squeaking that followed were beyond description.
Several hundred wild cats and wolves being roasted slowly alive together
would not have compared with it. The sparks were burning holes in the
goblins, and the smoke that now fell from the roof made the air too thick for
even their eyes to see through. Soon they were falling over one another and
rolling in heaps on the floor, biting and kicking and fighting as if they had
all gone mad. Suddenly a sword flashed in its own light. Bilbo saw it go right
through the great goblin as he stood dumbfounded in the middle of his rage.
He fell dead and the goblin soldiers fled before the sword shrieking into the
darkness. The sword went back into its sheath. Follow me quick," said a voice
fierce and quiet. And before Bilbull understood what had happened, he was
trotting along again, as fast as he could trot at the end of the line, down
more dark passages, with the yells of the goblin hall growing fainter behind
him. A pale light was leading them on.
"Quicker, quicker," said the voice. "The torches will soon be relet." Half a
minute, said Dory, who was at the back next to Bilbo, and a decent fellow. He
made the hobbit scramble on his shoulders as best he could with his tied
hands, and then off they all went at a run with a clink clink of chains, and
many a stumble, since they had no hands to steady themselves with. Not for a
long while did they stop, and by that time they must have been right down in
the very mountain's heart. Then Gandalf lit up his wand. Of course, it was
Gandalf, but just then they were too busy to ask how he got there. He took
out his sword again and again it flashed in the dark by itself. It burned with a
rage that made it gleam if goblins were about. Now it was bright as blue flame
for delight and the killing of the great lord of the cave. It made no trouble
whatever of cutting through the goblin chains and setting all the prisoners
free as quickly as possible. This sword's name was Glamring the faux
hammer if you remember. The goblins just called it beater and hated it worse than
biter if possible. Orchrist too had been saved, for Christ too had been saved.
Gandalf had brought it along as well, snatching it from one of the terrified
guards. Gandalf thought of most things, and though he could not do everything,
he could do a great deal for friends in a tight corner. Are we all here?" said
he, handing his sword back to Thoren with a bow. Let me see. One, that's
Thorin. 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11. Where are
Fely and Kelly? Here they are. 12 13.
And here's Mr. Baggins. 14. Wow. Wow.
Are we all? No ponies and no food and no knowing quite where we are and hordes of
angry goblins just behind. On we go. On they went. Gandalf was quite right. They
began to hear goblin noises and horrible cries far behind in the passages they
had come through. That sent them on faster than ever. And his poor Bilbo
could not possibly go half as fast for dwarves can roll along at a tremendous
pace. I can tell you when they have to, they took it in turn to carry him on
their backs. Still, goblins go faster than dwarves. And these goblins knew the
way better. They had made the paths themselves and were madly angry, so that
do what they could, the dwarves heard the cries and howls getting closer and
closer. Soon they could hear even the flap of the goblin feet, many, many feet
which seemed only just round the last corner. The blink of red torches could
be seen behind them in the tunnel they were following, and they were getting
deadly tired. "Why, oh, why did I ever leave my hobbit hole?" said poor Mr.
Baggins, bumping up and down on Bombber's back. "Why, oh, why did I ever
bring a wretched little hobbit on a treasure hunt," said poor Bomb, who was
fat and staggered along with the sweat dripping down his nose in his heat and
terror. "At this point, Gandalf fell behind, and Thoren with him. They turned
a sharp corner." "About turn!" he shouted. "Draw your sword, Thoren."
There was nothing else to be done, and the goblins did not like it. They came
scurrying around the corner in full cry, and found goblin cleaver and faux
hammers shining cold and bright right in their astonished eyes. The ones in front
dropped their torches and gave one yell before they were killed. The ones behind
yelled still more, and leaped back, knocking over those that were running
after them. Ber and beater, they shrieked, and soon they were all in
confusion, and most of them were hustling back the way they had come. It
was quite a long while before any of them dared to turn that corner. By that
time the dwarves had gone on again, a long, long way on into the dark tunnels
of the goblins realm. When the goblins discovered that, they put out their
torches, and they slipped on soft shoes, and they chose out their very quickest
runners with the sharpest ears and eyes.
These ran forward as swift as weasels in the dark, and with hardly any more noise
than bats. That is why neither Bilbo nor the dwarves, nor even Gandalf heard them
coming, nor did they see them. But they were seen by the goblins that ran
silently up behind, for Gandalf was letting his wand give out a faint light
to help the dwarves as they went along.
Quite suddenly, Dory, now at the back again, carrying Bilbo, was grabbed from
behind in the dark. He shouted and fell, and the hobbit rolled off his shoulders
into the blackness, bumped his head on hard rock, and remembered nothing more.